Finding Aid for Mary C. Bromage papers, 1862-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mary C. Bromage papers 1862-1994, 1923-1980
Bromage, Mary Cogan.
4 linear feet
9564 Aa 2
Professor of Written Communication in the School of Business Administration of the University of Michigan; writer on Irish history; correspondence, family history, newspaper editorials, photographs, and topical files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was received from Susanna Bromage Paterson (Donor no. 8329 ) in 1995.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Mary C. Bromage was born on October 13, 1906 in Massachusetts to James J. and Sarah Edith Ives Cogan. She attended public high school in Wakefield and Peabody, Massachusetts from 1920 through 1924. From 1924 to 1925, Bromage worked as a reporter for two Boston newspapers. During this same time, she was enrolled at Radcliffe College, earning her bachelor of arts degree (summa cum laude) in 1928. Her fields of concentration for her bachelor's degree included English literature, American and European government, world history, philosophy, Latin, French and German. Upon graduation, she married Arthur Watson Bromage (see separate Arthur Bromage finding aid). She continued her education at the University of Michigan, receiving her master's degree in 1932. The topic of her master's thesis was a comparative analysis of the treatment of Irish history in the medieval period.
In addition to her personal scholarly interests and family obligations, Mary Bromage continually took on other responsibilities. She was chief administrative officer for the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration in Washington, D.C from 1943 to 1944 and acting Dean of Women at the University of Michigan from 1944 to 1950. She was chief editorial writer for the Ann Arbor News from 1950 to 1955 and from 1954 to 1974 she was a lecturer in the English Department and professor in the School of Business Administration at the University of Michigan. Bromage was an author and Professor Emerita of Written Communication at the School of Business Administration at the University of Michigan. She also taught written communication for national business firms and government agencies. She instructed executives on clear writing and communication with employees. She conducted workshops and seminars in the United States, Canada, Europe, the Far East, Latin America and Africa.
Mary Bromage received many awards throughout her life. As a result of her editorials in the Ann Arbor News, the Freedom Foundation of Valley Forge awarded her its "certificate of recognition in bringing about a better understanding of the American way of life." The U.S. Department of Agriculture's Graduate School selected her to receive its annual "award of merit" and its award as "the most outstanding instructor at the Center," electing her to its Hall of Fame. In 1974, she was designated an Outstanding Educator of America. The U.S. Army Audit Agency also awarded her a Certificate of Appreciation. In 1991, the National Guard presented her with its medal for "outstanding support." In 1992, the Postal Inspection Service presented her with a special award in recognition of her "valuable contributions."
Much of her focus in her published writings was on Ireland and written communication. Bromage's book DeValera and the March of a Nation (1956, 1957, 1962, 1964, 1967) was published in Great Britain and the United States. Other books she had published were Cases in Written Communication (1964 and 1971), Churchill and Ireland (1964), Writing for Business (1971) and Writing Audit Reports (1979 and 1984 in Spanish). Many professional and academic journals have carried her articles on Irish nationalism as well as on written communication and writing audit reports.
She both participated in television and radio programs and wrote about topics of interest. Bromage was a host for University of Michigan television programs between 1954 and 1955 and a participant in 1974 and 1977. She was also involved in several radio programs involving Ireland and communications.
Bromage spent much of her time traveling outside the United States for research and lectures. She was a resident in Dublin, Ireland from 1936 through 1937. She spent time traveling in Great Britain, continental Europe, Korea, Japan, and Russia.
She was a member of Phi Beta Kappa, Women of the University Faculty, League of Women Voters, Midwest Case Research Association, American Committee on Irish Studies, Conference on British Studies, and the University of Michigan Research Club. She was appointed to the board of the University's Institute of Labor and Industrial Relations. She received the Citation of Honor from the Regents of the University of Michigan for her "notable career" as an author and teacher and for her "contributions to the academic leadership of the University."
She and her husband Arthur had one daughter, Susanna Bromage Paterson, six grandchildren and twelve great grandchildren. Mary Bromage died on January 3, 1995 at her daughter's home in Berkeley, California. She had been preceded in death by her husband, Arthur Bromage.
The Mary C. Bromage papers are divided into five series: Correspondence, Family History, Newspaper Editorials, Photographs and Topical.
Subjects:
Bromage, Mary Cogan.; Ann Arbor news.; Bromage, Arthur W. (Arthur Watson), 1904-1979.; Ireland.; De Valera, Eamonn, 1882-1975.; Bavaria (Germany)--Politics and government--1945.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bromage, Mary Cogan.; Bromage, Arthur W. (Arthur Watson), 1904-1979.; World War, 1939-1945.
Contributors:
Bromage, Arthur W. (Arthur Watson), 1904-1979.; Cogan, James J.; Ives, Sarah Edith.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Correspondence 1936-1992
  The Correspondence series (.7 linear feet; 1923-1993) is the strongest series of this collection. It contains many letters from her husband, Arthur Bromage, as well as other family members, friends and acquaintances. It is organized partly chronologically and partly alphabetically, mainly for individuals with substantial concentrations of correspondence.
  - 1942-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1978 (Box 1)
  - 1963-1993 (Box 1)
  - Bromage, Arthur W.
    - Excerpts February 1944-August 1945 (Box 1)
    - 1936 (Box 1)
    - January-February, 1944 (Box 1)
    - March-April, 1944 (Box 1)
    - May-June, 1944 (Box 1)
    - July-August, 1944 (Box 1)
    - September-October, 1944 (Box 1)
    - November-December, 1944 (Box 1)
    - January-February, 1945 (Box 1)
    - March-April, 1945 (Box 1)
    - May-June, 1945 (Box 1)
    - July-October, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Coffey, Ruth B. 1964, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Cogan, David 1957-1993 (Box 1)
  - Cogan, James and S. Edith 1937-1953 (Box 1)
  - DeValera, Eamon and Sile 1961-1981 (Box 1)
  - Grandchildren 1976-1995 (Box 1)
  - Ives, James E. (Uncle Ned) 1933-1938 (Box 1)
  - McGraw-Hill 1993 (Box 1)
  - O'Brien, Sophie 1954 (Box 1)
  - Paterson, Susanna Bromage 1953-1993 (Box 1)
- Family History
  The Family History series (.3 linear feet; 1862-1989) consists of information that Mary C. Bromage had gathered and saved about her family. It contains a diary written by her grandfather in 1862 and information on Sarah Edith Ives, her physician mother from 1892 to 1983, and her father Reverend, James J. Cogan from 1931 to 1980. It is organized alphabetically.
  - Biography (Box 1)
  - Bromage, Arthur (written by Mary C. Bromage for great grandchildren) undated (Box 1)
  - Bromage, Mary Cogan, transcript and cassette tapes of an interview 1990 (Box 1)
  - Bromage, Susanna and John Paterson (Box 1)
  - Cogan, James J. (father), 5 inch reel recording (Box 2)
  - Cogan, Sarah Edith Ives (mother) (Box 2)
  - Education 1921-1928 (Box 2)
  - Fall River and Beyond (Box 2)
  - Ives and Cogan Family Tree (Box 2)
  - Ives, J.T. Bostock (grandfather) 1862 (Box 2)
  - Ives, S. Mary (aunt) (Box 2)
  - Manor Lodge (the Ives Home) 1977-1979 (photograph) (Box 2)
  - Summary Written by Mary C. Bromage 1989 (Box 2)
  - Wedding Prayer Written by James J. Cogan 1941 (Box 2)
- Newspaper Editorials
  The Newspaper Editorials series (3 folders and 6 bound volumes; 1950-1954) is composed of bound volumes of Bromage's editorials for the Ann Arbor News. The volumes are organized chronologically.
  - Undated (Box 2)
  - Unpublished (Box 2)
  - 1950 (Box 2)
  - 1951 (Box 2)
  - 1952-1953 (Box 2)
  - 1953 (Box 2)
  - 1954, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Photographs
  The Photograph series (.5 linear feet; 1891-1988) includes pictures of her mother, her husband in the military, and group photos of seminars which she or her husband conducted. The photographs have been organized according to the subject of the picture and then arranged alphabetically.
  - Bromage, Arthur 1911-1970 (Box 2)
  - Bromage Family 1946, undated (Box 2)
  - Bromage, Arthur and Mary Together 1925-1928, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Bromage, Mary C. 1907-1926, 1930, 1966-1982 (Box 3)
  - Bromage, Mary C. Teaching at the University of Michigan 1946-1954 (Box 3)
  - Cogan, Edith Ives 1891-1931 (Box 3)
  - Cogan Family 1943-1961, undated (Box 3)
  - Friends and Associates 1951-1962 (Box 3)
  - Ireland 1936-1975 (Box 3)
  - Ives Family 1900-1905, undated (Box 3)
  - Paterson, Susanna Bromage and Family 1936-1975 (Box 3)
  - Writing Seminars (Mary and Arthur Bromage) 1961-1988 (Box 3)
- Topical
  The final series, Topical (2 linear feet; 1923-1994), contains general material about the variety of activities in which Bromage participated. Included are book reviews of Bromage's writings, information collected while she was writing her book on DeValera (autographs from two Irish presidents and an Irish Nationalist leader as well as her notes and diary while she resided in Ireland), her notes on her unpublished writings and short stories, and material that Bromage used in teaching at the University of Michigan and in the seminars that she conducted.
  - Article Review, "Defensive Writing," 1971 (Box 3)
  - Awards 1950, 1973-1979, 1992 (Box 3)
  - Bibliography (Box 3)
  - Book Reviews
    - Cases In Written Communication undated (Box 3)
    - Cases In Written Communication II 1967 (Box 3)
    - Churchill and Ireland 1964-1967 (Box 3)
    - DeValera and the March of a Nation 1956-1957 (Box 3)
    - Writing Audit Reports 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - Writing for Business 1964-1965 (Box 3)
  - Bromage, Arthur's Military Experience (Box 3)
  - Diary
    - 1953 (Box 3)
    - 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    - Traveling
      - England 1973 (Box 3)
      - Korea 1979 (Box 3)
      - Moscow 1986 (Box 3)
      - Munich 1988 (Box 3)
  - Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award 1976 (Box 3)
  - Instructor Contracts 1994 (Box 3)
  - Ireland
    - Autographed Material 1939, 1957, 1973 (Box 3)
    - DeValera
      - Background 1942-1953 (Box 3)
      - Book 1963 (Box 3)
      - Photographs, 1918-1955 (Box 3)
    - Diary, 1953 (Box 3)
    - Lectures 1977-1992 (Box 3)
    - O'Brien, Sophie
      - Excerpts undated (Box 3)
      - Writings
        - "An Old Woman's Recollections," undated (Box 3)
        - "Glimpses of a Long Life," undated (Box 3)
        - "Paradise," undated (Box 3)
    - Travel 1957, 1966, 1977-1992, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Manuscript
    - "Ireland's Nationalist Leadership is a 20th Century Prototype?" undated (Box 4)
    - "Lady to the Last," undated (Box 4)
    - "Nationalist Leadership--The Irish Prototype," undated (Box 4)
    - "Recollected Glimpses of Eugene O'Neill in Provincetown, Mass." 1984 (Box 4)
    - "Sacred Fount," undated (Box 4)
    - Short Stories undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Short Stories 1924-1979 (Box 4)
    - "The Tenets of Force In The Role of a Nationalist Leader," undated (Box 4)
    - "Two Short Stories," (submitted for the Major Fiction Award) undated (Box 4)
    - Untitled and undated (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Story 1923 (Box 4)
  - Passports 1970, 1977, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Personal Honors 1976, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Recognition in the Press 1978-1992 (Box 4)
  - Speeches 1983-1993 (Box 4)
  - Synopsis Pilot Report Writing Seminar 1965 (Box 4)
  - Teaching Material
    - Audit Reports undated (Box 4)
    - Correspondence Course, Business In Writing 1992 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence Course, Practical Writing for Business 1965 (Box 4)
    - Course Evaluation for Graduate School United States Department of Agriculture 1991-1993 (Box 4)
    - Executive Education Center undated (Box 4)
    - Foreign Communication undated (Box 4)
    - Government Audit Training Institute 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - Investigative Writings 1986 (Box 4)
    - Speaker Evaluation at University of Michigan 1989-1991 (Box 4)
    - Transparencies Originals undated (Box 4)
    - Written Communication undated (Box 4)
    - Writing and Re-Writing undated (Box 4)
  - Transcripts of Interviews done for Book on Ireland 1936, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
  - Travel in Europe 1960 (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan Recognition 1962-1992 (Box 4)
  - Workshop and Class Arrangements 1991-1994 (Box 4)